it's almost a cliché to say it's 70 percent of our entire planet, and of that, 95 percent is unexplored. So what we're trying to do with our expedition is to build and prove out a submersible that can go to any point on the bottom of the planet to explore the 60 percent of this planet that is still unexplored. DB: You need a pretty cool tool to do that, right? VV: Right. Now the tool is the submarine, the Limiting Factor. It's a state-of-the-art vessel
c'est un cliché de le dire - recouvrent 70% de notre planète, dont 95% sont inexplorés. Notre expédition a pour but de construire et de démontrer la valeur d'un submersible pouvant atteindre les profondeurs de la planète afin d'explorer les 60% de cette planète toujours inexplorés. DB : Et il vous faut un outil assez cool pour ça ? VV : En effet. L'outil est le sous-marin le Limiting Factor : un vaisseau très perfectionné,
supported by the support ship, the Pressure Drop. It has a two-person titanium sphere, 90 millimeters-thick, that keeps it at one atmosphere, and it has the ability to dive repeatedly down to the very deepest point of the ocean. DB: So like the SpaceX of ocean exploration? VV: Yeah, it's kind of the SpaceX of ocean exploration,
assisté par un navire de soutien, le Pressure Drop. Sa sphère en titane de 90 mm d'épaisseur, pour 2 personnes, maintient l'atmosphère constante et peut plonger à plusieurs reprises jusqu'au point le plus profond de l'océan. DB : Comme un SpaceX des océans ? VV : Oui, c'est une sorte de SpaceX des océans,
but I pilot my own vehicles. (Laughter) DB: Are you going to take Elon or...? VV: Yeah, I could take someone down there. So, Elon, if you're listening, I'll give you a ride in mine if you give me a ride in yours. (Laughter) DB: So tell us what it's like down there. I mean, we're talking about a place where the pressure is so intense that it's like putting an Eiffel Tower on your toe. VV: It's more than that. It's about 16,000 psi. So the issue is that we have this titanium sphere that allows us to go down to these extreme depths and come up repeatedly. That's never been done before. The Challenger Deep has been dived twice, once in 1960 and once in 2012 by James Cameron, and they went down and came back up and those were experimental craft. This is the first commercially certified submersible that can go up and down thousands of times with two people, including a scientist. We're very proud that we took down the deepest-diving British citizen in history just three weeks ago, Dr. Alan Jamieson of Newcastle University who was down with us on the Java Trench. DB: So, not too much freaks you out, is what I'm guessing. VV: Well, it's a lot different to go diving. If you're claustrophobic, you do not want to be in the submarine. We go down quite a distance and the missions typically last eight to nine hours in a confined space. It's very different from the career I had previously which was mountain climbing where you're in open spaces, the wind is whipping, it's very cold. This is the opposite. It's much more technical. It's much more about precision in using the instruments and troubleshooting anything that can go wrong. But if something really goes wrong in the submersible, you're not going to know it. (Laughter) DB: So you're afraid of leaks is what you're saying.
mais je pilote mes propres engins. (Rires) DB : Vous comptez emmener Elon ? VV : Oui, je pourrais emmener quelqu'un. Elon, si tu nous écoutes, je t'emmène faire un tour si tu m'emmènes dans le tien. (Rires) DB : Alors, c'est comment en-dessous ? On parle d'un endroit où la pression est aussi forte qu'une Tour Eiffel sur un doigt de pied. VV : Oh plus que ça. Environ 1,1 kilobar. Notre sphère en titane nous permet de plonger à des profondeurs extrêmes et de remonter de multiples fois. C'est une grande première. Le Challenger Deep a plongé deux fois, en 1960 et en 2012 avec James Cameron. Ils ont fait un aller-retour dans un vaisseau expérimental. Notre submersible commercialisable est le premier à pouvoir plonger et remonter des milliers de fois, avec 2 personnes dont un scientifique. Nous sommes très fiers qu'avec nous le Dr Alan Jamieson, de l'université de Newcastle a battu le record de plongée pour un citoyen britannique dans la fosse de Java il y a 3 semaines. DB : J'ai l'impression que vous n'avez peur de rien. VV : La plongée, c'est particulier. Si vous êtes claustrophobe, n'allez pas dans un sous-marin. La distance est longue et les missions durent 8 à 9 heures dans un espace confiné. C'est très différent de ma carrière précédente, l'alpinisme, avec ses grands espaces, le vent, le froid. Là, c'est l'inverse. C'est bien plus technique. Il faut être précis avec les instruments et savoir intervenir en cas de problème. Mais s'il y a un gros problème avec le sous-marin, on ne s'en rendra pas compte. (Rires) DB : Vous avez peur des fuites alors ?
VV: Leaks are not good, but if it's a leak that's happening, it's not that bad because if it was really bad you wouldn't know it, again, but -- you know, fire in the capsule, that wouldn't be good either, but it's actually a very safe submersible. I like to say I don't trust a lot of things in life, but I do trust titanium, I trust math and I trust finite element analysis, which is how you figure out whether or not things like this can survive these extraordinary pressures and conditions. DB: And that sphere is so perfectly machined, right? This is a truly unique craft. VV: That was the real trick -- is actually building a titanium sphere that was accurate to within .1 percent of machine. Titanium is a hard metal to work and a lot of people haven't figured it out, but we were very fortunate. Our extraordinary team was able to make an almost perfect sphere, which when you're subjecting something to pressure, that's the strongest geometry you can have. When I'm in the submersible and that hatch closes, I'm confident that I'm going to go down and come back up. DB: And that's the thing you double-check -- that the hatch is closed? VV: There are only two rules in diving a submarine. Number one is close the hatch securely. Number two is go back to rule number one. DB: Alright so, Atlantic Ocean: check. Southern Ocean: check. VV: No one has ever dived the Southern Ocean before. I know why. It's really, really hostile. The weather is awful.
VV : Les fuites, ce n'est pas bon. Si on s'aperçoit d'une fuite, ce n'est pas trop grave, Et si c'est grave, on ne s'en rendra pas compte. Un feu dans la capsule ne serait pas bon non plus. Mais notre submersible est très sûr. Je fais confiance à très peu de choses dans la vie, mais je me fie au titane, aux maths et à l'analyse par éléments finis, qui servent à déterminer si de tels objets peuvent endurer ces conditions et pressions extrêmes. DB : Et cette sphère a été parfaitement élaborée, n'est-ce pas ? C'est une réalisation remarquable. VV : C'était le plus compliqué, construire une sphère en titane avec une précision de 0,1%. Le titane est dur à travailler et beaucoup ont du mal à s'en servir, mais nous sommes chanceux. Notre équipe formidable a construit une sphère quasi-parfaite, la forme géométrique la plus apte à résister à la pression. Quand la trappe d'accès se referme sur moi, je suis confiant que je plongerai et referai surface. DB : Et c'est ce que vous vérifiez bien ? Que la trappe est fermée ? VV : Il y a seulement deux règles à suivre. Règle n°1 : Bien fermer la trappe. Règle n°2 : Retourner à la règle n°1. DB : L'océan Atlantique, c'est fait. L'océan Austral, c'est fait. VV : Personne n'avait exploré l'océan Austral. Je sais pourquoi. Il est très, très hostile. Le temps est abominable.
The word collision comes to mind. But we did that one, yes. Glad that's over -- DB: Yeah -- VV: Thank you. (Applause) DB: It's like you're racing through it. And now the Indian Ocean, as Kelly mentioned. VV: Yeah, that was three weeks ago. We were fortunate enough to actually solve the mystery. If someone had asked me three weeks ago, "What is the deepest point in the Indian Ocean?" -- no one really knew. There were two candidates,
Le mot « collision » me vient à l'esprit. Mais on l'a fait, oui. Content que ce soit fini. DB : Oui. VV: Merci. (Applaudissements) DB : Vous ne perdez pas de temps. Et maintenant l'océan Indien, comme l'a dit Kelly. VV : Oui, il y a trois semaines. Nous avons eu le privilège de résoudre le mystère. Si on m'avait demandé il y a trois semaines : « Quel y est le point le plus profond ? », personne ne le savait. Il y avait deux candidats,
one off of Western Australia and one in the Java Trench. We have this wonderful ship with a brilliant sonar. We mapped both of them. We sent landers down to the bottom and verified. It's actually in the center portion of the Java Trench, which is where no one thought it was. In fact, every time we've completed one of our major dives,
à l'ouest de l'Australie et dans la fosse de Java. On a un navire fantastique avec un très bon sonar. On les a cartographiés. On a déployé des atterrisseurs pour vérifier. Le point est au centre de la fosse de Java. Personne ne pensait qu'il serait là. D'ailleurs, après chaque plongée majeure,
we have to run off to Wikipedia and change it because it's completely wrong. (Laughter) DB: So it probably takes longer to get down there than the time you're able to spend down there? VV: No, we actually spend quite a bit of time. I have four days of oxygen supply in the vessel. If I'm down there for four days, something's gone so wrong I'm probably not going to use it, but it's about three hours down to the deepest part of the ocean
on s'empresse de corriger Wikipédia, car ils ont tout faux. (Rires) DB : Vous passez plus de temps à descendre que de temps dans les profondeurs ? VV : Non, on passe beaucoup de temps dans le fond. J'ai une réserve d'oxygène de quatre jours dans le vaisseau. Si je reste au fond quatre jours, c'est qu'il y a eu un problème, je n'en aurai plus besoin. Il faut trois heures pour atteindre le point le plus profond.
and then we can spend usually three or four hours and then another three hours up. So you don't want to stay in there for more than 10 or 11 hours.
On y passe ensuite trois ou quatre heures, et trois heures pour remonter. Ce n'est pas bon d'y rester plus de 10 ou 11 heures.
It can get a little tight. DB: Alright, so the bottom of the Indian Ocean. And this is something that no one besides you has ever seen before -- VV: This is actually imagery from one of our robotic landers. On the bottom right you can actually see a robust assfish -- that's what it's actually called. (Laughter) But you can see from the left a creature that's never been seen before. It's actually a bottom-dwelling jellyfish called a stalked ascidian, and none of them have ever looked like this before. It actually has a small child at the bottom of its stalk, and it just drifted across beautifully. So every single dive we have gone on, even though we're only down there for a couple of hours, we have found three or four new species because these are places that have been isolated for billions of years and no human being has ever been down there to film them or take samples. And so this is extraordinary for us -- (Applause) So what we are hoping -- the main objective of our mission is to build this tool. This tool is a door, because with this tool, we'll be able to make more of them potentially and take scientists down to do thousands of dives, to open that door to exploration and find things that we had no idea even existed. DB: And so more people have been to space than the bottom of the ocean. You're one of three. You're going to up that number, you're going to give it away. VV: Yeah, three people have dived to the bottom of the Pacific Ocean. The USS Trieste in 1960 with two individuals. James Cameron in 2012 with his Deep Sea Challenger -- thank you, Jim, great sub. This is a third-generation technology. We're not only going to try and go down, actually in two weeks, but we're going to try and do it multiple times, which has never been done before. If we can do that, we'll have proven the technology and that door will not just go open, it will stay open. (Applause) DB: Fantastic. Good luck. VV: Thank you very much. DB: Thank you.
On y est à l'étroit. DB : Ok : donc le fond de l'océan Indien. Quelque chose que vous seul avez vu. VV : Voici les images d'un de nos atterrisseurs. En bas à droite, vous pouvez voir une donzelle, c'est son vrai nom. (Rires) Et à gauche, une créature jamais vue auparavant. C'est un animal gélatineux à queue de la famille des ascidies, à l'aspect très différent du reste de la famille. Elle a un petit alevin accroché au bout de sa queue et nage gracieusement devant la caméra. Durant chacune de nos plongées, bien que nous n'y soyons restés que quelques heures, nous avons découvert trois ou quatre espèces, car ces endroits ont été isolés pendant des milliards d'années et aucun humain ne s'y était aventuré pour filmer ou récolter des échantillons. Donc pour nous, c'est extraordinaire. (Applaudissements) Ce que nous espérons, notre objectif principal, c'est de créer un outil, qui ouvrira une porte, car avec cet outil, on pourra en construire d'autres, emmener des milliers de scientifiques en plongée et ouvrir cette nouvelle porte d'exploration pour découvrir des choses dont on ne connaissait pas l'existence. DB : Plus de personnes sont allées dans l'espace que dans le fond de l'océan ? Vous êtes un des trois. Vous allez faire augmenter ce nombre. VV : Oui. Trois personnes ont atteint le fond de l'océan Pacifique. Le USS Trieste en 1960, avec deux hommes à bord. James Cameron en 2012 avec son Deep Sea Challenger. Merci James, super sous-marin ! Nous sommes la troisième génération. Dans deux semaines, nous n'allons pas juste plonger, nous allons plonger de multiples fois, ce qui n'a jamais été fait. Si nous réussissons, notre technologie sera éprouvée et la porte s'ouvrira mais surtout restera ouverte. (Applaudissements) DB : Bravo. Bonne chance. VV : Merci beaucoup. DB : Merci.
VV: Thank you all. (Applause)
VV : Merci à tous. (Applaudissements)